# Fernando Romulo da Silva

| Software Engineer | Java 5...17 | Java & Jakarta EE | Spring Framework | SQL | NoSQL | Docker | Kubernetes | | JavaScript | TypeScript | React |

Address: Cedo Feita, Porto - Portugal, Personal Page: <a href="https://fernando-romulo-silva.github.io/personal-page">https://fernando-romulo-silva.github.io/personal-page</a>

Cell Phone: +351 914-090-874, E-mail: fernando.romulo.silva@gmail.com

Relocation: Canada, EUA, Ireland, UK and Australia

## **PROFILE SUMMARY**

I am a senior full-stack certified software engineer, highly motivated by Java platform and JavaScript technologies. Although my primary qualifications are Java back-end, front-end server-side, and SQL databases, I have also worked with JavaScript front-end and NoSQL databases.

I have been actively contributing to teams in order to complete tasks, meet goals, and share knowledge. I have experience in analysis, design, coding, testing (automated and manual), and delivering applications like REST and SOAP web services, console applications, libraries, web applications, batch jobs, web crawlers, and desktop applications.

During my more than 15 years of experience, I have worked in a few business sectors like ERP, content management systems, employee benefits solutions, insurance provider solutions, credit reporting agencies (credit bureau), and financial solutions.

# **EXPERIENCE**

# • Senior Java Software Engineer, 04/2022

Dalenys - Porto - Portugal

I develop and maintain cloud-native financial applications (marketplace and data lake applications) using Java, Spring Boot, RabbitMQ, GCP, JavaScript, Typescript, React, MongoDB, and MySQL. I have been troubleshooting, resolving complex technical problems, and collaborating with my team to achieve its objectives.

#### **Activities:**

- Participate actively in Scrum meetings.
- Presenting demonstrations for users and other developers.
- Fix and update front-end applications.
- Fix and develop new features back-end (Rest API and Messaging) and docs OpenAPI (Swagger).
- Create automated tests and test other developers' tasks.
- Code review on merge request.
- Deploy applications (CI/CD).

### Senior Java Software Engineer, 12/2019 to 03/2022

Boa Vista SCPC - Barueri, SP - Brazil

I developed cloud-native credit bureau applications (debt checking, renegotiating debts, and credit score provider) using Spring Boot, Docker, Kubernetes, GCP, Google Pub/Sub, Redis, PostgreSQL, and MySQL Database Server. I improved Java applications by leveraging innovative Docker and Spring technologies to enhance performance and reliability.

# **Activities:**

- Participate actively in Kanban meetings.
- Create and improve Docker and K8s on the GCP cloud.
- Fix and create new features back-end (Rest API, Messaging, and batch) and docs OpenAPI (Swagger).
- Create automated tests.
- Adapt and enhance code to Sonar measurements.
- Create application documentation.

# • Senior Java Software Engineer, 04/2015 to 12/2019

Fleetcor VB Serviços - São Paulo, SP - Brazil

I developed web crawlers and employee benefits solutions using Java, JSoup, Apache HttpClient, HtmlUnit, Spring, JAX-WS, JAX-RS, Wildfly, Jetty, Tomcat, and Oracle Database Server. To increase performance on web navigation, I utilized multi-thread processing. Additionally, I designed and implemented several other features, including authentication, session management, and error handling.

#### **Activities**:

- Create and update Web crawler applications with multi-thread processing.
- Fix and develop new features back-end (Rest API, SOAP, Messaging, and batch).
- Training junior developers.
- Adapt JEE applications on the cloud.

# Mid Level Java Developer, 06/2014 to 04/2015

BNP Paribas Cardif - São Paulo, SP - Brazil

I developed and maintained Java applications for insurance providers, utilizing Java, Spring, Web Services SOAP, Tomcat, Jetty, and SQL Server. Additionally, I have revamped some applications developed on Java web (JSP, Servlet, Taglib, etc.), leveraging the Spring framework for improved efficiency and functionality.

#### Activities:

- Create and update SQL Server queries and procedures.
- Fix and develop new features back-end (SOAP WS).
- Training users and product owners.
- Integrate software components and third-party programs with applications.

# • Junior/Mid Level Java Developer, 09/2009 to 12/2013

VB Serviços - São Paulo, SP - Brazil

As a Java Developer, I worked extensively with employee benefits software solutions utilizing Java Enterprise Edition (JSF, EJB, CDI, JSP, Servlet, JMS, JAX-WS, and JAX-RS), Oracle Database Server, and Wildfly servers. I developed comprehensive back-end software, and front-end pages server-side.

#### Activities:

- Create and update JSF pages.
- Fix and develop new features back-end (EJB, SOAP WS, and JMS).
- Create scripts for deploying applications.
- Recommend and execute improvements.

# Junior Java Developer, 04/2008 to 08/2009

Vetor Web - São Paulo, SP - Brazil

I developed innovative interfaces for content management systems with advanced features using JavaScript, Java, JQuery, JSP, JSF, Spring, Tomcat, and MySQL.

#### **Activities:**

- Improving pages JSP with Javascript and JQuery framework.
- Maintain up-to-date documentation about business and technical guides.
- Deploy applications on web containers.

# • Junior Delphi and PL/SQL Developer, 04/2007 to 04/2008

**DB1** – Maringá, Paraná – Brazil

I was a Delphi and Oracle PL/SQL developer working on various ERP projects and had extensive experience creating and maintaining applications for medium to large wholesale companies.

#### **Activities:**

- Create and update Oracle DB procedures, functions, and triggers.
- Testing and evaluating new Delphi forms.
- Configure applications on computer clients.

# **SKILLS**

• Languages: I am a native Portuguese speaker and an advanced English speaker.

## Java:

- ◆ Versions: JDK 5 until JDK 17, GraalVm, DCEVM and HotSwapAgent.
- Libraries: JUnit, TestNG, AssertJ, Mockito, HtmlUnit, JSoup, ApacheUtils, OpenAPI, OpenFeign, QueryDSL, Guava, etc.
- ◆ **Tools:** Ant, Maven, Gradle, Spotbugs, PMD, and Checkstyle.

# **♦** Frameworks:

- Spring: Spring Framework, Spring Boot, Spring Security, Spring Data, Spring Batch and Spring MVC.
- JEE: JSF, EJB, JTA, JPA, CDI, JAX-WS, JAX-RS, JMS, batch Processing, etc.
- Others: Quarkus, Hibernate and Swing.

#### JavaScript:

- Version: JavaScript ES6 and Typescript.
- Libraries: React, React Router, Redux, Tanstack Query, Lodash, Axios, Jest and JQuery.
- Tools: JSLint, Npm, Yarn, and Webpack.

- Messaging: RabbitMQ, JMS (JEE provider and ActiveMQ Artemis), and Google Pub/Sub.
- Data Bases:
  - SQL: Oracle, PostgreSQL, SQL Server and MySQL.
  - PL/SQL: Oracle and SQL Server.
  - ◆ NoSQL: MongoDB and Redis.
- Infrastructure: Virtual Box, Docker, Docker Compose, and Kubernetes.
- Cloud: Google Cloud Platform (GCP), Rancher (private cloud).
- Version Control: Git, Github, Bitbucket and Gitlab.
- IDES: Eclipse, Visual Studio Code, Dbeaver, and MongoDB Compass.
- Servers: Wildfly, Glassfish, Tomcat, Undertow, and Jetty.
- Operation Systems: Windows desktop (all flavors) and Ubuntu Linux.
- Project Management:
  - Frameworks: Scrum (daily, task breakdown, grooming, planning, and retro), Kanban (daily, replenishment).
  - **Software:** Jira, Kanbanize, Microsoft Team Foundation and Redmine.
- Architecture: Event-driven architecture, Hexagonal architecture, Microservices, Monolith, and CQRS.
- Others: SOLID, Design Patterns, Object Oriented Design, Domain Driven Design, UML, and TDD.

## **EDUCATION**

- Postgraduate Degree Software Engineering Specialization, 03/2018 12/2020
  Pontifica Universidade Católica de São Paulo
  Specialization course with emphasis on software development and engineering using new technologies.
- Technical Course W1 Advanced Web Interface Development, 02/2014 to 03/2014 Global Code – São Paulo, SP – Brazil Coursework to learn web technologies like HTML5, XPath, JPath, Javascript, and JQuery.
- Technical Course Java Web Development, 06/2009 to 09/2009
  Caelum São Paulo, SP Brazil
  Coursework for learning Java Web technologies, JSP, Servlet, Struts, and JSF.
- Bachelor of Science Computer Science, 03/2002 to 12/2006
  UNOESTE Presidente Prudente SP Brazil
  Computer science major with emphasis on math, computer system knowledge, programming, developing computer tools, and software design.

# **CERTIFICATIONS**

- Oracle Java EE 7 Application Developer
- Oracle Java SE 8 Programmer
- Oracle Certified Master, Java SE 6 Developer
- Sun Certified Java Programmer 5

# RECENT PROJECTS

Company: Dalenys

**Project:** Frontend Data Lake (New features)

Stack: TypeScript, React 18, Axios, Jest, Yarn, EsLint

Role: Senior Software Engineer

Description: This a front-end application for the next project described. On this application, I fixed and

updated React JS pages.

Steps: • Updated functions and layouts

• Update/create configs files

Company: Dalenys

**Project:** API for Data Lake (New features)

Stack: Java 17, Spring Boot 3.0, JUnit, AssertJ, MongoDB, RabbitMQ, Docker, Kubernetes and GCP

Role: Senior Software Engineer

**Description:** This API create scheduled reports that read data from a big data structure expose its results on

line. I intensively used automated tests to guarantee the quality of its development.

Steps: • Create domains classes and tests

• Update/create services classes and tests

• Update/create endpoint classes and tests

• Update/create OpenAPI (Swagger) documentation

Company: Boa Vista SCPC

**Project:** API for Layouts (New Project)

Stack: Java 11, Spring Boot 2.5, Spring Security, JUnit, AssertJ, MySQL, Docker, Kubernetes and GCP

Role: Senior Software Engineer

**Description:** This API provides file layouts on JSON and XML formats to be used on batch processing on GCP.

Due to layouts having to follow strict rules, the application has to validate a lot of situations; I used automated tests like unit (TDD), integration, and acceptance tests (Spring Mock MVC) to

solve this problem.

**Steps:** • Create domains classes and tests

• Create services classes and tests

· Create endpoint classes and tests

Create OpenAPI (Swagger) documentation

Create documentation files (readme.md)

· Create Dockerfile

• Create Kubernets yml files (service, configMap, deployement, kustomization)

Company: Boa Vista SCPC

**Project:** Batch Processing For Debts (New Project)

Stack: Java 11, Spring Boot 2.5, Spring Batch, JUnit, AssertJ, PostgreSQL, Redis, Docker, Kubernetes

and GCP

Role: Senior Software Engineer

Description: This batch application reads specific files, usually 10GB, treats them, and stores the data

(credit score) on a Redis Hashes. The business rules were simple, but some analysis had to be

done.

Steps: • Create domains classes and tests

· Create services classes and tests

· Create batch classes and tests

· Create documentation files (readme.md)

Create Dockerfile

• Create Kubernets yml files (service, cron job, kustomization)

Company: Fleetcor VB Serviços

Project: Benefits buyer (Maintenance and Refactor)

Stack: Java 11, Wildfly, JEE, Spring Boot, OracleSQL, Docker

Role: Senior Software Engineer

Description: Refactoring was done by splitting some specific modules (navigation) and transforming a

monolithic architecture application towards micro-service architecture.

Steps: • Update/create domains classes

• Update/create services classes

• Create/create documetation classes

Company: Fleetcor VB Serviços

Project: Job Scheduler (New Project)

Stack: Java 11, JMS, Spring Boot, MySQL, Docker

Role: Senior Software Engineer

**Description:** This application is a job executor for other applications, listening requests from Rest API, SOAP,

and JMS. But some JSF pages was developed to create executions, too.

**Steps:** • Create domains classes

• Create services classes

· Create endpoint classes

· Create JMS client

Create Dockerfile